בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. Today's דף Daf is י"ג Yud Gimmel
13, and we're going to pick up, I'm just going to quickly
reread from the משנה Mishna on י"ב עמוד ב'. Yud Beit Amud
Beit. I think it was covered on שבת, Shabbos, but I'd like
to just start from there. So we're continuing to deal with cases
about business dealings with non-Jews, particularly in the context of עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah, and we've moved from the opening משנה Mishna which is
before their holidays, and the משנה Mishna that listed their holidays, and
then there was a question about going to the town where there's
an עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, and the question of what it meant
was unclear. רמב"ם Rambam says it means just an idol, but anyway,
the simple sense is that it means that there's a pagan holiday
going on, or maybe it means a market day specifically in honor
of a pagan god, which led to very important discussions yesterday about
מראית עין, Marit Ayin, doing things that look like you are either
worshipping עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah or going to worship עבודה זרה. Avodah
Zarah.
And now we pick up with the משנה Mishna on י"ב עמוד
ב' Yud Beit Amud Beit that continues going back more to the
theme of doing business with them, and let's take a look. עיר
שיש בה עבודת כוכבים, Ir sheyesh ba avodat kochavim, a city that
has idolatry in it. The basic debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot is whether this means it is a יום איד, Yom Eid,
a pagan holiday, and then this is about doing business on a
pagan holiday, or whether this means that, forget the pagan holidays, this
is a specific market day that is devoted to a particular pagan
god. It's not a holiday, but a market day, and the relevance
being that the business that's done in the market itself, it's not
just about doing business in general, business in the market itself is
somehow
connected to that pagan god. So we're going to go with that
understanding, that it's specifically a market day dedicated to a particular pagan
god. והיו בו חנויות מעוטרות ושאינן מעוטרות, Vehayu vo chanuyot me'utarot veshe'einan
me'utarot, and there were in this market stores that were, some were
bedecked and some were not bedecked, you know, crowned, what's it called,
like decorated and so on, and obviously the implication being that those
that were decorated were specifically in honor of this pagan god.
זה היה מעשה בבית שאן, Zeh hayah ma'aseh biBeis She'an, that was
during בית שאן, Beis She'an, which is a very cosmopolitan city, a
lot of Jews and non-Jews living there. ואמרו חכמים, Ve'amru Chachamim, and
the חכמים Chachamim said, המעוטרות אסורות ושאינן מעוטרות מותרות. Hame'utarot asurot veshe'einan
me'utarot mutarot. Those that are bedecked, those that are decorated are forbidden,
to presumably to buy from there, and those that are not are
permissible even though the market day is maybe devoted to the pagan
god, it does not mean that every transaction is forbidden. And therefore
if it's not in a store that is devoted to that, it
is not a problem. רש"י, Rashi, who understands that this case here
is not just talking about a market day but actually a יום
איד, Yom Eid, a holiday itself, has to deal with the question
that תוספות Tosafot raised from the outset, which is, can we do
business with them on a יום איד? Yom Eid? Because even if
the store itself is not decorated and is not devoted to that
pagan god, but it's still doing business on a יום איד. Yom
Eid. And this leads רש"י Rashi to here to say something תוספות
Tosafot said way at the beginning of the מסכת, Masechet, which is
that maybe it's only forbidden to sell them items because then they
would use those items in their worship,
but maybe it's actually permissible to buy items from them. Anyway, that's
an ongoing discussion whether it is permissible to buy items on their
יום איד. Yom Eid. But more simply here we're not talking about
a יום איד, Yom Eid, we're just talking about a market day,
and the ones that are decorated are in honor of this pagan
god. And therefore we'll see in a minute why that makes it
forbidden. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi,
לא שנו אלא מעוטרות בורד והדס. Lo shanu ela me'utarot bevered vehadas.
It's only a problem if they are decorated with myrtle and roses.
דקמתהני מריחא. Dekamtahni meireicha. And the problem there is that these myrtle
and roses are somehow from an עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, you know,
maybe they're I don't know grown in a garden devoted to the
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, maybe they're actually even worse, maybe they're things
that were offered up as an offering to the עבודה זרה. Avodah
Zarah. So we'll worry about that later, exactly how something becomes so
connected to an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah that it becomes forbidden in
benefit. But that would be the context here. These are things that
are directly, let's you know, connected to the idol itself. And therefore
you can't derive benefit from an idol, you can't derive benefit from
things that are connected to it, you know, maybe they were bedecked
around the idol. Anyway, and therefore it's forbidden to derive benefit, so
you go to buy something in the store and ah, you get
the beautiful smell. So now you're deriving benefit from something that is
forbidden, אסור בהנאה. Assur behana'ah. דקמתהני מריחא, Dekamtahni meireicha,
you're getting benefits from the smell. אבל מעוטרות בפירות מותרות. Aval me'utarot
bepeirot mutarot. But if it's only decorated with fruit, so you can't
smell the fruit, it's permissible even though you know that this store
somehow... is connected to a pagan god, but you're not deriving any
benefit. מאי טעמא, mai ta’ama, what's the reason? דאמר קרא לא ידבק
בידך מאומה מן החרם. d’amar kra lo yidbak b’yadcha m’uma min hacharem.
Nothing from what is under the ban should cleave to your hands.
נהנה הוא דאסור אבל מהנה שרי, nehanehu d’asur aval mehane shari,
deriving benefit from things connected to an idol is forbidden; giving benefit
is permissible. Now before we get to that, that seems like a
radical statement. One quick mention about the benefit of the roses and
the myrtle. תוספות Tosafot asks the question: is it true that things
that are forbidden in הנאה hana'ah you are not allowed to smell?
Is smell considered a normal type of הנאה? hana'ah? You would think
so. It's not eating, but you know it's bodily pleasure. You say
a ברכה, bracha, so you would think so. That's certainly implied by
this גמרא. Gemara.
And תוספות Tosafot asks from another גמרא Gemara that it's maybe a
little bit more questionable. So תוספות Tosafot makes two points. First he
says, things that are normally made for giving off an aroma like
roses and myrtle, you know that's the normal thing, that they're seen
as aromatic, then smelling is forbidden. Something that it's not that's normally
the benefit you derive from it, right, and you happen to smell
it, okay, that would be considered לאו דרך הנאה, lav derech hana'ah,
not the normal way of deriving benefit, and would not be forbidden
by איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. The other point תוספות Tosafot says is
maybe even if it's not the normal way here, sometimes even things
that are not normal, there are certain types of things that you
can't get even unusual benefits from them when the verse does not
say that something is forbidden in הנאה hana'ah by using the word
of אכילה achila but by using other words to indicate that it's
totally off-limits, like by כלאים kilayim it says תקדש, tikdash, by בשר
בחלב basar bechalav it says לא תבשל, lo tevashel, okay, and by
עבודה זרה avoda zara it says לא ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם
lo yidbak b’yadcha m’uma min hacharem because of החרם. hacharem. That means
totally off-limits. That means even לא דרך הנאתו, lo derech hana’ato, even
הנאה hana’ah that is not the normal way of deriving benefit. So
for those things, maybe even if it wasn't roses and myrtle it
would be forbidden, even if it's not considered normal. But for other
types of things that are forbidden in הנאה, hana’ah, תוספות Tosafot says
it could be that smelling is not a problem because that is
not the normal way of deriving benefit. So again, just an interesting
parenthetical point: is smell considered a type of הנאה? hana’ah? תוספות Tosafot
basically answers yes if that's normal, like it is normal for things
that are aromatic like roses and myrtle, and B even if it's
not normal it could be a problem by עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
עבודה זרה avoda zara might be forbidden even in non-normal ways of
הנאה. hana’ah. Okay, but we're going to leave it for that. Okay,
but back to the major point that ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says,
the only problem is deriving benefit. It is not a problem of
actually giving benefit. Now that is a little strange. Really, I can
go ahead and I can just donate money to the temple of
the pagan god and that's not a problem of actually giving benefit?
And תוספות Tosafot gives a whole list of cases where the גמרא
Gemara makes it clear that it does see it's a problem of
giving benefit. So how could ריש לקיש Resh Lakish say it's not
a problem? So תוספות Tosafot says that maybe ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
only means in this particular case there's something unique about this particular
case we'll see about in a minute. Anyway, that's an important question.
Does ריש לקיש Resh Lakish really mean in general he's not bothered
with giving benefit to an עבודה זרה? avoda zara? Okay, now the
question is what would you transgress? So let's take a look at
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן אמר אפילו מותרות בפירות נמי אסור,
Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu mutarot bepeirot nami asur, even if it's just
decked with fruit it's forbidden. קל וחומר, kal vachomer, it's a קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, נהנה אסור מהנה לא כל שכן? nehane asur mehane
lo kol shekein? If you're not allowed to derive benefit, you know
once it's connected to the עבודה זרה avoda zara it's off-limits and
therefore you can't connect it to yourself, that's learned from the verse.
So to actually do something that would like benefit the עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, right, raise it up, you know show your support of
it, how much more so should that be forbidden? Now the question
still is, is that a biblical forbidden? I mean he makes a
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, it's a pretty convincing type of a logical
argument. Okay, but is it really based on the verse? Is that
לא ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם? lo yidbak b'yadcha m'uma min hacharem?
That maybe yes, maybe giving something is also connecting to the thing
under the ban. But anyway, it's not exactly clear what exactly is
the nature of what makes it forbidden. And we'll read a תוספות
Tosafot in a minute. But you know it could be that it's
more like rabbinic than it is biblical even though he makes a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. And it could be that part of the
problem is as we all I think are intuiting that it shows
somehow that you support it, right, that you think that this is
actually, you know, so you know you're connected to it in a
way not just that you get some benefit but you're actually connected
to it in the sense of actually, you know, giving your monetary
support behind it. Okay, so that actually is clearly at least a
symbolic problem. How are you מהנה mehane here? We didn't spell that
out. What happens when you buy stuff from one of these stores?
So the presumption is רש"י Rashi has two explanations. You know one
explanation is and it makes a difference also thinking about the sort
of symbolic meaning of what you're doing. One explanation is that they
charge a tax today because it is the because this is the
market day devoted to Dionysus, you know there's a two percent tax
on every sale and it's not a sales tax, it's a Dionysus
tax, and that two percent goes to the temple of Dionysus. Okay,
so that's one way that's מהנה. mehane. Your money even though you're
not doing it and saying oh I'd like to
"Would you care to give a dollar for Dionysus?" You know, like
they say at the supermarket, "Would you care to give a dollar
for this cause?" So you're not even conscious you're doing it, they're
just charging you the tax, you have no choice in it, etc.,
but nevertheless, that's where the money is going. Okay, the other explanation,
that's at least we can understand the problematics. The other explanation רשי
Rashi says is that the store actually is owned by the church
of Dionysus. So therefore they are making the profit. All right. So
that's also like a little bit different because there you're not like
giving the money for the sake of the church, it's more like
the profit that's being made. Anyway, it also raises interesting questions. And
let's say the profit is going to the priests of Dionysus and
they're using it to pay for their food bills, you know. It's
not going to build the church, it's not going
to make a, you know, some type of a pedestal or to
build the next idol or whatever it might be. So it's not
exactly clear A, what is the context in which it's being given,
how much is it like money that is earmarked for this or
how much is it profit that's being made, how much is it
what you're intending to do or is it a necessary byproduct, right?
And the other thing is that what is the money going to
actually directly connected to the idol, right, or the temple, or is
it maybe to support the people that work there, you know, and
the priests? So there's like a lot of factors, which might be
why ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says it's permissible, right? תוספות Tosafot is
very bothered that the clear גמרות Gemaras say it's forbidden, but there's
a lot of these factors to consider about what exactly are the
parameters. Let's read a little bit more, then I want to read
you an interesting תוספות Tosafot that was relevant for him. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: מיתיבי. Meiseh.
So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, "I will challenge you, ריש לקיש,
Reish Lakish, this idea that you say that it is permissible." רבי
נתן אומר, Rabbi Natan omer, רבי נתן Rabbi Natan says, יום שעבודת
כוכבים מנחת בו את המכס. Yom sheavodat kochavim menachat bo et hamaches.
There's a day sometimes where they waive the tax. Now this is
different. This is not, "Today it's a Dionysus day, 2% of all
sales go to or 2% tax that's going to go to the
Dionysus temple." What they say is, "Today this market is dedicated to
Dionysus, and normally there's a 2% sales tax on every sale, but
if you do something to honor Dionysus, we'll waive the sales tax,
the standard sales tax." Okay. יום... Yom... so
יום שעבודת כוכבים מנחת בו את המכס. Yom sheavodat kochavim menachat bo
et hamaches. The day that the... in honor of the god, they
waive the normal sales tax. מכריזין ואומרים. Machrizin veomrim.
They make an announcement and they say, כל מי שנוטל עטרה ויניח
בראשו ובראש חמורו. Kol mi shenotel atarah veyaniach berosho uverosh chamoro.
It sounds almost like a little bit like, you know, what was
it, אחשורוש, Achashverosh, put it on the head of the horse. "Anybody
who will take this crown and put it on his head and
on the head of the donkey in order presumably as an honor
of this holiday we're having or the market day we're having, okay,
לכבוד עבודת כוכבים, lichvod avodat kochavim,
in honor of our god Dionysus there, יניח לו את המכס. yaniach
lo et hamaches. Yes, יניח יניח. yaniach yaniach.
We will waive the tax and you don't have to pay your
standard sales tax or your import tax, whatever מכס maches is. ואם
לאו אל יניח לו את המכס. Veim lav al yaniach lo et
hamaches. And if not, it won't be waived for you. So יהודי
Yehudi שנמצא שם, shenimtsa sham, I think this is the first time
we find the word יהודי, Yehudi, pretty fascinating, right? It certainly reflects
that they're dealing with a very concrete reality that was familiar to
them. A Jew who's found there, מה יעשה? mah yaaseh? What should
he do? יניח, yaniach,
should he put the crown on? נמצא נהנה. nimtsa neheneh. Then he
will be deriving benefit. How is he deriving benefit? So רשי Rashi
assumes that the crown does not mean some gold thing, it means
like a wreath, okay. And therefore this wreath, it's sort of like
the thing before about the roses and the myrtle.
You don't have to pay the tax.
No, תוספות Tosafot says that is not נהנה neheneh because it's your
own money, so not charging you is not נהנה. neheneh. That's what
תוספות Tosafot says. רשי Rashi says, I mean תוספות Tosafot recognizes the
possibility of saying what you're saying, but he sides with רשי, Rashi,
at least he whatever explains רשי. Rashi. That's just keeping your own
money. The נהנה neheneh is, רשי Rashi says that these are like,
say again, myrtles and roses that are connected with the god and
therefore you're deriving, you're smelling, you're deriving sort of a physical benefit.
It's a different kind of pleasure, no benefit.
Maybe. But I'm less bothered. You could say like Michael says that
there's also a נהנה neheneh that the tax isn't being charged. But
what I'm more bothered about by all of this, and I'm shocked
that רשי Rashi and תוספות Tosafot don't discuss this, is forget נהנה.
neheneh. Like if you're putting on a crown in honor of Dionysus,
that's not like close to, I'm not saying it's one of the
four עבודות avodot שחייב מיתה, shechayav misa, but at least there should
be the, you know, the act of honor, you know, the מנשק,
mishakek, hugging and kissing and whatever, you know, should be a type
of a way of showing honor to a god. I mean my
god, it seems like close to an act of עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. Like, oh, we're bothered by the נהנה? neheneh? So I might
not be... there's something in which I'm not formally understanding like the
full cultural context. But still, it seems like it's saying like, I
don't know, I'm participating in the holiday, I'm supporting the god. I
really don't understand at all how come it's limiting to an issue
of נהנה. neheneh. לא יניח, Lo yaniach, don't put it on. נמצא
מהנה, nimtsa mehaneh, then you're going to pay the tax and the
tax presumably... probably is going to go to the temple, okay, although
it’s funny, it sounded like it was a standard tax that was
being waived, but anyway, now it sounds like the tax is specifically
going to go connected to the god. Okay, so what are you
going to do? You can’t be נהנה, nehaneh, you can’t be מהנה.
mehaneh. So therefore what you can do is, don’t do business on
that day. מכאן אמרו, Mikan amru, הנושא ונותן בשוק של עבודה כוכבים,
hanoseh venotein beshuk shel avodah kochavim, if somebody goes ahead and does
business in this market day of this god, בהמה תעקר, behemah te’akeir,
so you’re not allowed to, and if you do, there’s going to
be pretty heavy consequences. We’re going to basically treat everything that you
bought or money that you made during the transactions in this market
day as if they
are objects of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, or objects connected to עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. And they have to completely be destroyed. Okay, בהמה
תעקר, behemah te’akeir, an animal has to be mutilated, פירות כסות וכלים
ירקבו, peirot kesut vekeilim yirakevu, fruit and vessels and clothing should have
to be left to rot, מעות וכלי מתכות, ma’ot uchelei matachot, things
that are made of metal or money if you sold something, יוליכם
לים המלח, yolicheim leyam hamelach, you have to throw them to the
Dead Sea. Okay, ואיזהו עיקור, Ve’eizehu ikur, by the way, we said
this before, what’s considered this type of a maiming, a mutilating, המנשה
פרסותיה מן הארכובה ולמטה, hamenasheh parsoteha min ha’arkuvah ulemattah, you basically like
you cut the tendons from the ankle down. Okay, and תוספות Tosafot
says that that means that even that is sufficient, you don’t have
to do more. Okay, so anyway, תני מיהא, Tani miha, so first
of all that’s pretty radical. I also want to remind us, although
we said you’re not allowed to do business on a יום איד,
yom eid, and there’s a debate of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan if you did business before the יום איד
yom eid whether it would be forbidden, but everybody agreed if you
did business on the יום איד yom eid it’s forbidden. It did
not say there, that’s different, that was a יום איד yom eid
and that wasn’t in the context of the market itself that was
dedicated to the god. That was just somebody goes ahead into a
normal grocery store and it happens to be the יום איד. yom
eid. So this did not just forbid it, this is a very
harsh what we do with those objects. It’s not clear whether we
would take the same steps if it was just סתם stam business
on a יום איד. yom eid. Okay, but this is business in
the market of dedicated to the god, okay, where there’s this נהנה
nehaneh and מהנה mehaneh problem.
תני מיהא, Tani miha, we teach nevertheless, יניח נמצא נהנה לא יניח
נמצא מהנה. yaniach nimtsa nehaneh lo yaniach nimtsa mehaneh. So you see
a proof like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that there is a problem
with being מהנה, mehaneh, with paying this tax that somehow is going
to go to the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
So what do you do, you’re there, you need, you didn’t bring
lunch, you need to plan ahead.
Plan ahead, go somewhere that’s not that market. So אמר רבי יהושע
בריה דרב אידי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua breih deRav Idi, קסבר ריש לקיש,
Kasavar Reish Lakish, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish holds, פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי
נתן. Pligi rabanan aleih deRabbi Natan. That yeah, that was רבי נתן's
Rabbi Natan opinion, but the Rabbis disagree. The Rabbis say it would
not be a problem to actually go ahead and to not put
on the crown and to pay the tax. ואנא דאמרי כרבנן, Ve’ana
de’amri kerabanan, I hold like the Rabbis דפליגי עליה דרבי נתן, depligi
aleih deRabbi Natan, that argued on it. So by the way, תוספות
Tosafot claims that this is the only case that ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish allows מהנה. mehaneh. Because normally of course he would agree if
there’s a standard tax being charged and the money is paid to
Dionysus, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would agree with רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
He wanted it to be that pretty much everybody agrees that מהנה
mehaneh is forbidden. The one case according to תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot
limits it this way, that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish allows מהנה mehaneh
is that the reason I’m paying the tax is because I’m refusing
to put on the crown. So therefore it is actually an act
of disrespect to the god. So even though the money goes to
the god, says תוספות, Tosafot, but it’s through an act of disrespect.
And therefore ריש לקיש Reish Lakish allows it, which means by the
way again that part of the question here is the symbolic statement
that is being made. So that allows ריש לקיש Reish Lakish to
say that in this case it would actually not be a problem.
Okay, but ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says fine, I think that the
Rabbis don’t permit it and therefore I think that רבי נתן Rabbi
Natan doesn’t permit it, I think the Rabbis would permit it in
this case. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says,
ורבי יוחנן סבר לא פליגי. VeRabbi Yochanan savar lo pligi. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan holds no, everybody agrees that it is forbidden. This statement
of רבי נתן Rabbi Natan is agreed with by the Rabbis, you
can’t do business because of מהנה. mehaneh. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ולא פליגי, Velo pligi, is it really true they don’t argue? According
to רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? והא תניא, Veha tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא Baraita exactly this, that the Rabbis do argue and the
Rabbis permit it. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan we’re going to show
that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was aware of this ברייתא. Baraita. What
did we teach in the
ברייתא? Baraita? הולכין ליריד של עובדי כוכבים, Holchin leyarid shel ovdei chochavim,
ולוקחין מהם בהמה עבדים ושפחות בתים שדות וכרמים, velokechin meihem behemah avadim
ushfachot batim sadot ucheramim, you can go to the market days of
these idols, of these pagan gods, and purchase
there
cattle, slaves, slave men, slave women, houses, real estate, fields, vineyards, וכותב
ומעלה בערכאות שלהם, vechoteiv uma’aleh be’arka’ot shelahem, and not only that, you
can register the documents in their courts, and you don’t have to
be afraid of a type of a problem of like בחוקותיהם, bechukoteihem,
not even בחוקותיהם, bechukoteihem, אלה המשפטים אשר תשים לפניהם, Eileh hamishpatim asher
tasim lifneihem, that you’re not supposed to use their courts, you’re supposed
to use our courts. All of this is allowed why? מפני שהוא
כמציל מידם, Mipnei shehu kematzil miyadam, because you’re like saving it from
their hands. Now this is very important because a number of the
תקנות takanot that we’re going to see in עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
specifically
especially coming up pretty soon, specifically are in the context of trying
to strengthen the Jewish presence in the land of Israel and trying
to get it that we’re... so we try to like reclaim our
rights to the land of Israel. So we try to buy property
and we make special exceptions when we're able to buy property, you're
even allowed to get a שטר shtar written on שבת, Shabbos, not
directly, you have a non-Jew write it or whatever the case might
be, but you know, you're allowed to do very special things and
that's real estate. But even not real estate, even things that are
part of, you know, like what it means to really have a
presence in the land. Slaves, right, means that you can sort of
like control the land better. Cattle, right, all these types of things.
So cattle and slaves, it doesn't say you can go ahead and
buy like nice suits, okay, but these are the things and we're
going to see a whole range of it, also things you're not
allowed to sell to them because you don't want this is the
land of Israel.
You don't say that, but
right, but it says well correct, but that's like the larger context
here. We're going to sort of get similar to, it's going to
be clear in a minute, okay, that idea. But yes, I think
that the larger context is the land of Israel, similarly there are
going to be about things you're not allowed to sell them because
that would be the reverse. Okay, so this is about doing things
to sort of strengthen our presence in the land of Israel and
therefore you're allowed to do it משום כמציל מידם mishum kematzil mi-yadam
because you're like salvaging it from their hands, taking it away. Now,
at least that's the way I read that this is about the
land of Israel, we'll see maybe it's a little maybe open to
some possible different reasons in the גמרא. Gemara. But I think that's
pretty clear. Anyway, and it says ואם היה כהן, ve-im hayah Kohen,
now if you were a כהן, Kohen, מטמא בחוצה לארץ, mitamei be-chutz
la-aretz,
you can even go to חוצה לארץ chutz la-aretz which is considered
a rabbinic impurity, לדון ולערער עמהם, la-dun u-le-ar'er imahem,
to go into, you know, defend your claims, your real estate claims
against them, you know, because you're having a court case in Rome
or something. וכשם שמטמא בחוצה לארץ כך מטמא בבית הקברות, ve-keshem she-mitamei
be-chutz la-aretz kach mitamei be-veit ha-kevarot, you can even go into a
cemetery. So the גמרא Gemara says בית הקברות סלקא דעתך? beit ha-kevarot
salka da'atach? What do you mean you're going into a cemetery? That's
מדאורייתא, mi-de'oraisa, that's biblical. אלא בבית הפרס דרבנן. ella be-veit ha-peras de-rabbanan.
Fine.
Wait, you can't be in even a non-Jewish cemetery is מדאורייתא? mi-de'oraisa?
Alright, I don't know, but anyway, it was maybe it could have
given that answer. But it says a בית הפרס דרבנן, veit ha-peras
de-rabbanan, a rabbinic בית הפרס veit ha-peras which is an area in
which a grave has been overturned, so you have to can't walk
in the whole area because of a concern about little bits of
bone. Anyway, now that we're talking by the way about the fact
that a כהן Kohen can go to חוצה לארץ chutz la-aretz and
transgress rabbinic טומאה tumah for the sense of defending the claims to
the land of Israel, the real estate claims, we're going to say
other reasons in which a כהן Kohen is allowed to do this.
ומטמא ללמוד תורה ולישא אשה, u-mitamei lilmod Torah ve-lisa ishah, he can
go to חוצה לארץ chutz la-aretz also for the sake of learning
תורה Torah and getting married. Okay, these are big מצוות mitzvos and
therefore we were allowed this violation of this rabbinic
טומאה. tumah. אמר רבי יהודה אימתי בזמן שאין מוצא ללמוד, Amar Rabbi
Yehudah eimasai bi-zman she-ein motzei lilmod, if
there's no good ישיבה yeshiva to go to in Israel. אבל בזמן
שמוצא ללמוד, Aval bi-zman she-motzei lilmod, if you can find a good
place to learn here, אינו מטמא, eino mitamei, you can't go to
חוצה לארץ. chutz la-aretz. רבי יוסי אומר אפילו בזמן שמוצא ללמוד, Rabbi
Yossi omer afilu bi-zman she-motzei lilmod, even if there is a good
ישיבה yeshiva here, יטמא, yitamei, you can go to חוצה לארץ, chutz
la-aretz, לפי שאין אדם זוכה ללמוד מכל. lefi she-ein adam zocheh lilmod
mi-kol. You don't merit, you can't necessarily merit learning from everyone. You
say, what do you mean? We have a beautiful ישיבה yeshiva right
in our town. This guy feels he can only really be successful
in his learning going in this place in חוצה לארץ, chutz la-aretz,
that's enough, you basically person has, you know, some people are specifically
successful in certain places. It's actually an interesting question about כיבוד אב
ואם kibbud av va-eim as well. Somebody wants to go out of
town to learn in a ישיבה, yeshiva, the parents say no, we
have a good ישיבה yeshiva here, you stay here, you take care
of us, etc. Same types of issues come up. Okay, now. רבי
יוסי אומר אפילו בזמן שמוצא ללמוד יטמא וכן היה עושה. Rabbi Yossi
omer afilu bi-zman she-motzei lilmod yitamei ve-chen hayah oseh. אמר רבי יוסי
מעשה ביוסף הכהן, Amar Rabbi Yossi ma'aseh be-Yosef ha-Kohen, there's a story
with יוסף הכהן Yosef ha-Kohen שהלך אחר רבו לצידן. she-halach achar rabbo
le-Tzidan. He went after his master to צידן Tzidan ללמוד תורה, lilmod
Torah, and which is presumably in חוצה לארץ. chutz la-aretz. Okay, ואמר
רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי יוסי, ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke-Rabbi Yossi, we
rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that you are a כהן Kohen
is allowed to go to חוצה לארץ chutz la-aretz for the sake
of learning תורה, Torah, which is all a big digression about becoming
טמא tamei and going to חוצה לארץ chutz la-aretz for protecting your
claims to the land, which was a digression about being able to
buy these things at the market day in order to more retain
our claim to the land and our presence in the land. Yes,
go. This gets into what are the boundaries, because צידן Tzidan would
have been in שבט אשר Shevet Asher but it was not populated
by Jews at the time of. Right, so it might have had
טומאת חוצה לארץ, tumas chutz la-aretz, that's a good point. Okay, so
anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says you see that רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan holds of
this
ברייתא.
braisa. And this ברייתא braisa holds that you're allowed to do business
with them on their market day, okay, and we're not concerned about
the issue of מהנה. mehaneh. Now I have to tell you, I
am super bothered by this question in the גמרא, Gemara, because this
ברייתא braisa is specifically allowing you to do business, not because there's
not fundamentally a problem. There is fundamentally a problem doing business, but
there's an overriding concern of specifically these things. It doesn't say you're
allowed to buy, you know, food and clothes or whatever, specifically these
things which are animals, slaves, and land, which are about staking our
claim to the land, מציל מידם. matzil mi-yadam. So what's bothering the
גמרא? Gemara? That's why normally it would be forbidden. So either what's
bothering the גמרא Gemara is one of two things. Either that the
גמרא Gemara is still pointing out like, okay, presumably though, you know,
okay, who cares what the reason is, bottom line you're allowed to
do it. So why did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say you're forbidden
to do it if here at least on a wide range of
things you're allowed? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan should have made a blanket
statement that you're forbidden. That's one way of saying it. The other
way is that these two ברייתות braisos do contradict in the one
case of the בהמה. beheimah. Right, the previous ברייתא braisa did not
mention land and did not mention slaves, but it did mention that
if somebody bought a בהמה beheimah they have to destroy it, right?
בהמת תעקר, Behemat T’aker, remember that? So here at least it’s saying
that there is a debate, right? This ברייתא Baraita says the previous
ברייתא Baraita says that a בהמה Behemah is a problem, and this
ברייתא Baraita says a בהמה Behemah is okay. Anyway, bottom line is
that the גמרא Gemara is saying that it seems like this ברייתא
Baraita it’s okay, מהנה Mehane is okay. So how come even if
the reason it’s okay is because of להציל מידם, Lehatzil miyadam, you
know, for to retain this stuff under Jewish control, but it does
say it’s okay, so how did ר' יוחנן Reb Yochanan say that
it was forbidden? מהנה Mehane was forbidden.
What does תוספות Tosafot say about this?
Well, I’m going to get to that, let me just finish this
one line. So the גמרא Gemara says, thanks for reminding me, the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, אלמא פליגי, Alma pligi, you see that they
do debate, this ברייתא Baraita and the previous one, the one of
who was it, of רב יוסף? Rav Yosef? Who was the previous
one?
ר' נתן, Rebbi Natan, excuse me, you see that it does debate.
So אלמא פליגי. Alma pligi. אמר לך ר' יוחנן לעולם לא פליגי.
Amar lecha Reb Yochanan leolam lo pligi. They don’t debate. ולא קשיא
כאן בלוקח מן התגר. Velo kashya, kan belokeach min hataggar. When ר'
נתן Rebbi Natan that says you’re not allowed because of מהנה, Mehane,
that’s when you’re buying from a merchant, not from like, it’s not
a flea market, it’s somebody who’s in the business. So when you’re
buying from the merchants, the מכס, Meches, they charge a tax, and
that tax goes to the Dionysius
temple, so that’s מהנה. Mehane. כאן בלוקח מבעל הבית. Kan belokeach miba’al
habayis. Here it’s when you’re buying from a homeowner, it’s like a
flea market, not somebody who’s in the business, and because they don’t
take a tax, therefore it’s okay. Alright, so therefore he says, really,
everybody would say if you take a tax it’s forbidden. Good. The
only reason that this was permitted in this second ברייתא Baraita was
a scenario where it’s a homeowner and not somebody who’s in the
business, and therefore it is, what do you call it, right, what,
on Craigslist you can select whether it’s by sale by owner or
sale by, what’s the other selector? Dealer or something like that. And
so that’s it.
Okay, anyway. So that’s why it’s okay, so that’s why it’s okay.
Now, of course what’s troubling about this, as I said before, is,
so what? So this makes it sound like all of these special
allowances to buy slaves and land and all those things, that’s only
if you’re buying from a homeowner? You can’t do this if you’re
buying from a merchant? I don’t get it. Anyway, what do I
need a special allowance if I’m buying from a homeowner? So if
I’m buying from a homeowner, why should it be forbidden? I’m not
paying a tax, I’m not smelling the roses, okay, why should it
be forbidden? So it’s very strange. The obvious answer the גמרא Gemara
should have given is, the reason it’s allowed here is because there’s
an overriding issue of being able to, you know, to reclaim these
objects, you know, like the land. But anyway, so, and that certainly
seems like the thrust of it, that even if normally we’d have
a problem because you’re paying a מכס, Meches, here we’re going to
do a special thing to allow it. The way the גמרא Gemara
makes it sound is that like it’s only allowed when you’re not
actually paying the מכס, Meches, which completely loses the power of the
point that these are special allowances given.
Even if you know this homeowner’s going to use it for עבודה
זרה?
Avodah Zarah? No, no, the... what do you mean? No, the... that
you’re allowed to buy it from a homeowner when it’s because you’re
not paying... what are you going to use it? The money?
He’s still making a profit.
That we’re not dealing with יום איד, Yom ed, it’s not the
issue. Yes. All right, anyway. So, anyway, so that’s the issue, meaning,
okay, big חידוש. Chiddush. If they’re not charging a מכס Meches and
the money isn’t going to עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, it’s allowed. That’s,
okay, but again, that sort of completely undermines the point of this
ברייתא, Baraita, which is that even if there is a problem, it’s
allowed because of retaining this ownership. Now let me read you, before
we continue, this תוספות Tosafot about a certain practical reality they’re trying
to translate this. So take a look at this תוספות, Tosafot, קל
וחומר מהנה אסור מהנה לא כל שכן. Kal v’chomer mehane asur mehan’eh
lo kol she-ken. כתב רבינו ברוך. Katav Rabbeinu Baruch.
So רבינו ברוך Rabbeinu Baruch writes, אותו יריד שהכומר של עבודת כוכבים
לוקחין בו מכס מן המכס, Oso yarid she-komer shel avodat kokhavim lokhin
bo meches min hameches, so this was obviously a case he was
dealing with. And he was still assuming that Christianity was עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. And remember, even though תוספות Tosafot said before
that Christians are not considered to be עובדי עבודה זרה, Ovdei Avodah
Zarah, but Christianity is still עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And what that
means is, while it allows us to do business with Christians, if
you still consider Christianity עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, then you cannot do
anything that directly gets benefit from, let’s say, the Church as an
institution. Right, because that’s not about Christians. And you can’t do anything
that gives benefit to the Church as an institution. All right, so
that actually is means that the discussion here is very relevant. Because
if you’re not allowed to be מהנה Mehane and you’re still considering
Christianity עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah even for Christians, meaning, if you consider
Christianity עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, you know, only for Jews and not
for non-Jews, it’s an interesting question, and maybe you can benefit the
Church because I’m just supporting non-Jews in their permissible worship. Okay, or
maybe I can’t. Maybe since I’m connecting to something that for me
is an עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, maybe that’s a problem. That raises
a really interesting question, right? It’s עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah for me
and not for them, can I make a donation to the Church?
Okay, but anyway, but if it’s still עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah for
all of us, it’s just they’re not עובדי עבודה זרה, Ovdei Avodah
Zarah, מהנה’s Mehane going to be a problem. So now he’s dealing
with an issue. There’s a market, there’s a day where basically the
priests come, or the monks, שהכומר של עבודת כוכבים לוקחין בו מכס
מן המכס, she-komer shel avodat kokhavim lokhin bo meches min hameches, they
actually charge a tax from all the... from all the sale. מיד
*mi-yad* עם אותו מכס הוא לבנין עבודת כוכבים *im oto mechess hu
l-vinyan avodat kochavim*
if that's going to actually a building fund for the church, okay,
that's what I said also matters where exactly is the money going.
If it's going to pay for the food of the monks, big
deal. But if it's going for the building, okay, והעובד כוכבים מפרש
*ve-ha-oved kochavim mefaresh* כך וכך *kach ve-kach*. How much is it? Oh
it's ten dollars, ועוד פשוט לבנין עבודת כוכבים *ve-od pashut l-vinyan avodat
kochavim* plus another dollar or a quarter towards our church building fund.
He explicitly says that. Okay, and you don't have a choice, that's
what it costs. Like you don't have a choice when the storekeeper
says and it's another dollar for sales tax. You still have to
pay it, but it's exactly labeled that way. Okay, so ועוד פשוט
לבנין עבודת כוכבים *ve-od pashut l-vinyan avodat kochavim* אסור Assur, *assur*. You
can't do that. You can't buy something in that context where you're
going to be required to give something that's going to be labeled
as a donation to the church building fund. Okay, דמהנה אסור *de-mehaneh
assur* רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rav Yochanan*. ואף אם לא יזכר לבנין
עבודת כוכבים *ve-af im lo yizkar l-vinyan avodat kochavim* even if he
didn't explicitly label it, אלא אמר amar: אחר שפירש לו הסכום אמר
לו ועוד פשוט *ela amar achar she-peirash lo ha-schum amar lo ve-od
pashut*. He says, oh, it's you know it's ten dollars oh and
also an additional quarter. And he doesn't explicitly say why an additional
quarter. Okay, ונראה דאסור *ve-nireh de-assur*. It would seem it would still
be forbidden. כי מה שלא הזכיר לבנין עבודת כוכבים *ki mah she-lo
hizkir l-vinyan avodat kochavim* מפני שישראל הוא מניח *mipnei she-Yisrael hu mani'ach*.
He's just not saying it out of respect to the Jew because
he knows it would be uncomfortable for the Jew. But it's obvious
where that money is going and it's clearly an additional tax. ומכל
מקום אם לא היה מתנה הבנין היה נוטל לו בסכום הראשון *u-mi-kol
makom im lo haya matneh ha-vinyan haya notel lo be-schum ha-rishon*. It's
clear that were it not that they were doing a special building
fund, that it would have just been ten dollars, not the other
quarter. ונמצא הפשוט יוצא מכיסו של ישראל Yisrael. לבנין עבודת כוכבים *ve-nimtza
ha-pashut yotze mi-kiso shel Yisrael l-vinyan avodat kochavim*. It's going from your
pocket to the church building fund. So that should be a problem.
You are giving money
to the church, and if we're still considering that עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah, *avodah zarah*, you know that is going to be a problem.
והרב משה מקוצי כתב בספרו *ve-ha-rav Moshe mi-Kotzi katav be-sifro* כי אם
אמר סתם ועוד פשוט *ki im amar stam ve-od pashut* יכול להיות
דמותר *yachol lihyot de-mutar* שמא יתנהו לעניי עובדי כוכבים *shema yitenu l-aniyei
ovdei kochavim*. You never know.
Maybe they'll use it to go to some of their you know
to their services. Maybe they'll use it for their church for their
soup kitchen and they won't actually use it for their building fund.
So here it's very interesting, A, what is the money going for,
even if it's going you know to the temple to the church
etc. But also what's really interesting is translating it into their reality,
right? And and see also seeing that even though they allowed business
with Christians by not considering Christians עובדי עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah, *ovdei
avodah zarah*, right, they still to do direct benefit from or to
the church as an entity, that still was a problem. Yes, so
רש״י *Rashi* had his... yeah, a practical guy, whatever his name is.
Did I say רש״י *Rashi*?
Okay yeah, it's becoming less common, but there's still a number of
countries where direct tax funds support Christian churches.
Yeah, although that's an interesting question. It's sort
of specifically meaning, you know, if if when I pay my taxes,
all money is fungible, even it gets divided amongst a lot of
different things. You're saying there's a specific tax that's earmarked to go
specifically...
In some countries, yes, but Jews generally can get out of that.
But what's more common is a general tax to pay the salaries
of the clergy. They have that in England, they have that in
Norway.
Okay, but again, salaries is really less of an issue. And again,
the other question comes up, if once הלכה Halacha *halacha* develops that
Christianity is not עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah, *avodah zarah* for Christians, it
only is for Jews, it really raises a fascinating question about why
can I not, you know, be מהנה *mehaneh* the עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah *avodah zarah*? Is by being מהנה *mehaneh* the עבודה זרה avodah
zarah *avodah zarah* somehow like I am supporting these non-Jews in their
forbidden worship, and it wouldn't be a problem if they are non-Jews,
you know, if if for them it's not forbidden. But if it's
because לא ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם *lo yidbak be-yadcha me-umah min
ha-cherem*, which is what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* sounds like, forget the
non-Jew, it's my direct connection to this forbidden thing, right? So then
it should be a problem because for me it remains עבודה זרה
avodah zarah *avodah zarah*.
Yeah, here's what I was thinking. I was thinking about the you
know after Katrina, New Orleans, you know what I mean? And like
everything needs to be rebuilt. Right, then you get a whole bunch
of volunteers, can we go and rebuild the church? Right, you know
they have a soup kitchen there, but it's still a church.
So to your point to that. So that's exactly why I'm raising...
No I'm saying forget the money, it's like you're going to them...
I know. ...could even be worse according to this view, right?
I understand.
So that would be a problem. It depends. Once we say that
Christianity is not עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah. *avodah zarah* for Christians, it
might be okay. There are definitely פוסקים *poskim* that allowed donations to
be made, like for the building of a church that was destroyed
and so on, you know, because it's not... But that wasn't what's
interesting here, right. Right, well that תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* was dealing... this
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* was not... was not yet introducing the distinction which
is based on a different תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* which is actually the
way אחרונים *acharonim* read the later תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot*
himself never meant it, but anyway, based on the later distinction to
say it's עבודה avodah, זרה *avodah zarah* for Jews but not for
non-Jews. This תוספות Tosafos? *Tosafot* is assuming it's עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*
for everyone. It's just that Christians don't... aren't real עובדי עבודה זרה
*ovdei avodah zarah*, they're not real sincere in their worship.
That was the earlier one. Yeah, exactly. On the first דף. Exactly.
Okay, so wait, just so I understand, because you know, this—but at
this point in the תוספות Tosafos on the גמרא, Gemara that would
be אסור, right? Correct. But you're saying others, you know, whoever it
is,
as הלכה Halacha develops later, it's not so clear. Okay, so גמרא
Gemara says like this.
אמר מר, Amar Mar, so now we
taught, ובהמה תעקר, V'beheimah Te'aker, your—you maim the animal if it was
bought during this market day. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says ואיכא צער
בעלי חיים, V'eika Tzar Baalei Chayim, which is what תוספות Tosafos asked
earlier by the animal that was bought—that was being done for the—for
the death of the kings. Okay, so when you did this as
part of a ritual over the funeral of the kings. So here
the גמרא Gemara is asking, isn't there צער בעלי חיים, Tzar Baalei
Chayim, the animal is suffering? אמר אביי אמר רחמנא וסוסיהם תעקר. Amar
Abaye Amar Rachmana V'susiehem Te'aker. Now we learned by יהושע Yehoshua like
when they went into the land and they destroyed all their stuff
and it says of the—of the nations that they destroyed, the pagan
nations, and it said that you should, you know, maim their horses.
So we do the same here. Now of course that was a
specific מצוה Mitzvah of יהושע Yehoshua for conquering those nations, so we
can learn it like a general theme that things connected to עבודה
זרה, but obviously it's a loose connection and it's really a רבנן
Rabanan idea, it's a קנס, Knas, it's a fine. Exactly. So if
you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos תוספות Tosafos says, תוספות, Tosafos,
where's תוספות? Tosafos אמר קרא וסוסיהם תעקר אמר אביי אמר קרא וסוסיהם
תעקר. Amar Kra V'susiehem Te'aker Amar Abaye Amar Kra V'susiehem Te'aker. תוספות
Tosafos, says הקשה רב חננאל למאן דאמר צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא, Hiksha
Rav Chananel L'man De'amar Tzar Baalei Chayim De'oraisa, צער בעלי חיים Tzar
Baalei Chayim is biblical, מה ראיה מייתי מיהושע? Mah Re'ayah Meisi Mi'Yehoshua?
התם שאני התם דעל פי הדיבור הוא, Hatam Shani Hatam De'al Pi
HaDibbur Hu, that was a direct biblical, Torah—God's command. אבל הכא דרבי
קנס דרבנן היכי עבדינן היכי עקרינן ולעקור דבר מן התורה. Aval Hacha
Dirabi Knas De'Rabanan Heichi Avdinan Heichi Akrinan V'le'akor Davar Min HaTorah. Here
it's only רבנן, Rabanan, how can you uproot a biblical value of
צער בעלי חיים? Tzar Baalei Chayim? ויש לומר דבוודאי יש כוח ביד
חכמים לעקור היכא דנראה להם קצת לעקור. V'yesh L'omar Devadai Yesh Koach
B'yad Chachamim La'akor Heicha Dinira Lahem Ktzas La'akor. Yeah, rabbis sometimes can
override a biblical theme if they have a good reason to, and
then he gives an example. So anyway, this תוספות Tosafot is important
because it's consistent with the earlier תוספות Tosafot about why you do
this for the funeral of kings. And תוספות Tosafot says that was
a special exception because of the honor of a king is an
honor of all of כל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. For תוספות, Tosafot there
is no allowance of צער בעלי חיים Tzar Baalei Chayim when it
serves human needs or certain human, you know, human benefit. Both cases
that we allowed it, there were special exceptions, either for the sake
of עבודה זרה, putting down עבודה זרה, you know, rabbis sometimes have
the ability to override this value of צער בעלי חיים, Tzar Baalei
Chayim, or there was another value that weighed more, כבוד המלך כבוד
כל ישראל. Kvod HaMelech Kvod Klal Yisrael. But as a general principle,
you cannot do צער בעלי חיים Tzar Baalei Chayim to serve some
human benefit.
Meaning you don't have to worry about צער בעלי חיים Tzar Baalei
Chayim if it serves some human benefit?
No, you do have to worry. You are not permitted to inflict
צער בעלי חיים Tzar Baalei Chayim although you—for the sake of getting
human benefit. The only reason it is allowed here is that there
are special exceptions, right? The special exception that there's an עבודה זרה
concern, that it's the honor of a king. But without these extremely
narrow exceptions, we would not have permitted צער בעלי חיים Tzar Baalei
Chayim although just for the sake that it's benefiting humans. That is
in contrast to the רמב"ם Rambam and the—and the תרומת הדשן Trumas
HaDeshen and the way הלכה develops, which is anytime it serves human
benefit, it's permissible. If you believe that, you wouldn't have had his
questions to begin with. You wouldn't have called it עוקר דבר מן
התורה. Oker Davar Min HaTorah. Why it's עוקר דבר מן התורה, Oker
Davar Min HaTorah, it's permissible for the sake of human benefit. Okay,
but תוספות Tosafot understands no, the allowance is extremely narrow. But other
ראשונים Rishonim answer these questions by saying there's a general permission of
צער בעלי חיים Tzar Baalei Chayim for the sake of human benefit.
So the only time according to them it would be off is
if I just like feel
like cruelty in my heart?
Exactly. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר מר. Amar Mar. ואיזהו עיקור? Ve'eizehu Ikur? What is considered
maimed? מן הפרסה ולמטה, Min HaParsah Ul'mata, when you maim them from
like the—the ankle down. רמינהי, Reminihi, I'll ask you on this: אין
מקדישין ואין מעריכין ואין מחרימין בזמן הזה. Ein Makdishin V'ein Maarichin V'ein
Machrimin Bazman Hazeh. You don't sanctify objects nowadays. ואי הקדיש והעריך והחרים,
Ve'im Hikdish V'he'erich V'hecherim, if you sanctify them through any of these
different ways, you don't do it because then you're not allowed—there's no
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to give it to and it's got to
be sticking around and then you're going to be over on מעילה,
Me'ilah, you're going to be over on sort of deriving forbidden benefit.
So that's a dangerous thing to be doing. So if you do
this,
ובהמה תעקר, V'beheimah Te'aker, it's the same thing we've seen before, you
maim the animal, פירות כסות וכלים יירקבו, Peiros Ksuss V'keilim Yeirakvu, you
let the other stuff rot. מעות וכלי מתכות, Maos U'chlei Matachos, money
and and metal objects, יוליכם לים המלח, Yolichem L'Yam HaMelach, you throw
them into the Dead Sea. ואיזהו עיקור? Ve'eizehu Ikur? But here's the
question, because this ברייתא Braisa says what's considered עיקור? Ikur? נועל דלת
לפניה, Noel Delas L'faneha, not literally maiming them, it means you lock
the door in front of it, you lock them up in a
pen, ומתה מאליה, U'meisah Me'eileha, and it dies out of starvation. Right,
like חטאת המתה. Chatas HaMeisah. And of course if Rifka were here,
she would be protesting, rightly protesting about what about צער בעלי חיים?
Tzar Baalei Chayim? It's really fascinating that the גמרא Gemara here doesn't
ask about צער בעלי חיים. Tzar Baalei Chayim. I guess it would
give the same answer, you know, when there's some benefit being served
or whatever, or according to תוספות, Tosafot יש כוח ביד חכמים, Yesh
Koach B'yad Chachamim, if there's some bigger overriding principle, then sometimes we
can do it. Okay, and here the principle is to prevent the
issue of מעילה. Me'ilah. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says so you
see that it's not through direct maiming, so why is this different?
So the answer is obvious, it's different because it's קדשים. Kodashim. So
אמר מר... Amar Mar... Another question, by the way, to ask here
is why don't you just redeem it all on a פרוטה? perutah?
Right, the basic principle is that normally when you redeem הקדש, hekdesh,
something you sanctify to the temple, you're supposed to redeem it on
something of equal value. But בדיעבד, bedi'avad, if you did it on
even a penny, it works. And since הקדש hekdesh isn't around to
get the money and you're going to destroy this property anyway to
protect people from transgressing, why don't you redeem all of this stuff
on a penny and take the penny and throw it into ים
המלח? Yam HaMelach? So הלכתית halachit that actually would work. But part
of what's going on here is a קנס. knas. We want to
discourage people from being מקדיש makdish it in the first place. So
therefore in order to discourage you we're not going to let you
redeem it on a penny and throw the penny away, we want
you to throw everything away. Okay, if you actually did that, it
probably would work. Anyway, so the question is how come here it's
only indirect and it's not maiming if עיקור ikur means maiming? One
minute. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says: שאני התם משום
ביזוי קדשים. shani hatam mishum bizui kodashim.
Yeah, okay, we're not going to maim it. It's something sanctified. That
would be showing a disrespect. So we're just going to let it
die. Letting it die is not as... of course here what you're
doing by the other stuff is you're throwing it into ים סוף.
Yam Suf. You're letting it rot. Okay, but somehow that is deader
than actual mutilating of an animal. Leaving it to rot, I don't
know why throwing it in ים סוף Yam Suf is not disrespect.
But anyway, leaving it to... leaving it to die is not as,
like, disrespectful as actually mutilating it. So we're not going to actually
mutilate it. Okay, one minute. ונישחטיה נישחט... venishchetei nishchat... of course, if
it's עבודה זרה or if it's stuff that's a product of an
עבודה זרה market, we're more than happy to actually, you know, do...
do something mutilating and so on. So הגמרא haGemara says: if that's
the only issue, ונישחטיה נישחט. venishchetei nishchat. So why don't you just
destroy it without... without a way that's degraded, without a way that's,
you know, disrespectful? Why don't you just slaughter it? ונישחטיה נישחט, venishchetei
nishchat, that's what הגמרא haGemara says. אתו בהו לידי תקלה... atu behu
lidei takalah... then people will think it's kosher meat and come to
eat it.
תוספות Tosafot asks a question: why isn't this שחוטי חוץ? shchutei chutz?
So this becomes an interesting question. רש"י Rashi reads this whole גמרא
Gemara that you only sanctified it לבדק הבית. lebedek habayit. You didn't
sanctify it as a קרבן. korban. So then it can't be שחוטי
חוץ. shchutei chutz. תוספות Tosafot seems to be talking even in cases
where you might have sanctified it as a קרבן. korban. So תוספות
Tosafot actually... but if that in the possibility of that scenario, תוספות
says something pretty radical. Or it would not be an איסור issur
of שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz slaughtering a קרבן korban outside the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash when there's no בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Maybe it's
not radical, maybe it should be obvious. But anyway, it's pretty crazy
though if I were to now sanctify an animal and bring it
at my private במה, bamah, I would... because there's no בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, I wouldn't be עובר over שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. I
might be עובר over some other איסור, issur, whatever, אלא מנוחה ואנחה
לו. ella menucha ve'anacha lo. I might be עובר over some other
איסור issur about the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash being the unique place.
But anyway... anyway, that's fascinating. But let's assume we're talking about that
it's only הקדש hekdesh for בדק הבית. bedek habayit. So now the
גמרא Gemara says: ולשדייה גיסטרא. uleshadyei gistera. Okay, so but still instead
of mutilating it, why don't you basically just like cut it in
half? Meaning, now that sounds pretty mutilating as well. Right, like slaughter
from the back of its neck or something like that, that it
would not be considered mutilating and it also would not be... and
it would not be concerned that people would eat it.
Okay, ורש"י veRashi now has a problem... didn't we have that רש"י
Rashi earlier that you couldn't make something a נבלה? neveilah?
Oh, right, so yeah, that's true, that's according to that רש"י. Rashi.
Anyway, but here... okay. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אמר קרא: amar kra:
ונתצתם את מזבחותם. venitatztem et mizbechotam. You should destroy their altars. לא
תעשון כן לה' אלהיכם. lo taasun ken l'Adonai Eloheichem. Don't do that
to Hashem your God. So something that is actively destruction can't be
done. So maybe he would feel to kill it would be... would
be destroying and a violation of this, destroying הקדש, hekdesh,
whereas letting it die... and maybe... and maybe this goes back, now
it's not just maybe ביזוי, bizui, maybe mutilating is also considered destroying,
or maybe not. Maybe mutilating is ביזוי bizui but not destroying. You
didn't actually kill the thing. Okay, but locking it in is neither
ביזוי bizui nor destroying. Of course one wonders, I don't know, taking
the stuff and throwing it to ים המלח, Yam HaMelach, that's not
destroying? Maybe it's not, the thing is still around, it's just sinking
to the bottom of the sea. Okay, so you're just... you're not
actively destroying the object. So you can't actively destroy the object, that's...
that's the prohibition of לא תעשון כן לה' אלהיכם. lo taasun ken
l'Adonai Eloheichem. Mutilating it, whatever, actively mutilating it might be that, might
be considered just ביזוי. bizui. Letting it die is the solution. That's
what אביי Abaye says. רבא Rava אמר: here's why we don't... here's
why we don't mutilate it. מפני שנראה כמטיל מום בקדשים. mipnei shenira
kematil mum bekodashim. It's not because it's disrespectful, but it looks like
you're making a blemish, and you're prohibited to make a blemish in
a sacrifice. Now this isn't a sacrifice, we're going to go with
רש"י, Rashi, this is just בדק הבית. bedek habayit. But because it's
an animal, it's easily confused with a sacrifice. So that's... therefore it
looks like that, it looks like you're making a מום. mum. So
the גמרא Gemara says: נראה מום, nira mum, מום מעליא הוא. mum
me'alya hu. It is a מום. mum. Okay, so really it should
be כעושה מום ke'oseh mum in something that's נראה כקדשים, nira kekodashim,
not נראה כעושה מום. nira ke'oseh mum. Okay, but anyway, it's a
real מום, mum, maybe the thing isn't a sacrifice but it's still
a real מום. mum. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says no. הני מילי, hani milei, when would
it be a מום mum if this was a real sacrifice, a
real violation, בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, bizman sheBeit HaMikdash kayam, if there
was a בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, then if it was a sacrifice
and you made a מום, mum, then it would be a real
biblical violation, דחזי להקרבה, dechazi lehakravah, it could be brought.
Because even if it were a real sacrifice, if it wasn't just
בית קביא, Beis Kavya, it still wouldn't be a real violation without
a
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. The גמרא Gemara says ליתא במציאות. leisa b'metzius.
Really? Is that really true? Just because you can't bring it, there's
no violation? ולא הוי כמטיל מום בבעל מום. V'lo havei k'matil mum
b'baal mum. Let's say an animal already had a blemish, a sacrifice,
and you made another blemish. There's a debate about that, but according
to those that rule that that's a violation, you see that it's
a violation even if it can't be brought as a קרבן. korban.
If this really were a קרבן, korban, it would be a biblical
violation דאף גב דלא חזי להקרבה אסור. d'af gav d'lo chazi l'hakrava
asur. The גמרא Gemara says בעל מום, baal mum, ניהי דלא חזי
לגופיה לדמי חזי. nihei d'lo chazi l'gufei lidmei chazi. If there's a
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, then just because this animal has a blemish,
this animal still is a קרבן korban in potential. Why? My חטאת
Chatas has a blemish, what am I going to do with that?
Not my חטאת, Chatas, my עולה Olah has a blemish. What am
I going to do with that? My חטאת Chatas could be, anyway,
what am I going to do with it? I'm going to redeem
it on this money and use this money to buy another עולה.
Olah. This עולה Olah with a blemish when the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash is around is a קרבן korban in potential and therefore I
can't make a מום mum on it even though it itself cannot
be brought, the קדושה kedushah can be transferred and brought as a
קרבן, korban, so therefore the prohibition of מום mum still applies. But
if I have my עולה Olah when there's no בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, then actually even though it's unblemished, there would not be a
biblical violation to make a מום mum because there is no way
right now that either the animal or any proceeds from this animal
could be brought as a קרבן. korban. And since right now the
ability to bring it or its substitute as a קרבן korban is
not possible, there would not be a biblical violation of making a
מום. mum. And therefore the more so when it's not actually a
קרבן korban and just בית קביא, Beis Kavya, it's only a problem
that it's נראה כמום, nireh k'mum, but it's not the actual violation.
One minute.
ניהי דלא חזי לגופיה לדמי חזי. Nihei d'lo chazi l'gufei lidmei chazi.
In the case of a blemish when there is a בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, the money, the proceeds could be brought as a קרבן.
korban. לאפוקי הכא דלא לדמי חזי ולא לגופיה חזי. Lafukei hacha d'lo
lidmei chazi v'lo l'gufei chazi. It itself nor its proceeds can be
brought and therefore when there's no בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, there would
be no biblical violation of making a מום mum and all the
more so now when it's just a בית קביא. Beis Kavya. So
therefore that's not a biblical violation, but it's נראה, nireh, it doesn't
look good and therefore you do not directly blemish it, you lock
it up. In all these cases, you let them get destroyed so
somebody doesn't benefit. You don't actively destroy them because it's either looks
like you're making a מום mum or it's בזיון bizayon or it's
a violation of לא תעשון כן לה' אלהיכם, lo sa'asun ken l'Hashem
Elokeichem, you don't even mimic for those reasons. Yes.
So why didn't we do what you suggested, that you just put
it on a lower value פרוטה perutah and throw that in?
Because תוספות says we want to punish you for sanctifying when you
didn't have to sanctify.
My other question is just thinking about the way this contemporarily goes
on in a slightly different venue is פדיון הבן, Pidyon HaBen, right?
So there's no עבודה, there's no בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, there's no
anything. So why don't we say forget the five סלעים, selaim, here
take a penny? Why don't we do that?
No, פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen is different. פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen is
a debt that you owe the כהן. kohen. It's a מצוה, mitzvah,
etc., it's not transferring קדושה. kedushah. The question that you really want
to ask, which תוספות asks, is about a בכור בהמה, bechor behemah,
בכור בהמה bechor behemah where תוספות says there, since you didn't actually
do anything wrong, you could say you did something wrong, you could
have sold the ear to a נכרי, nochri, there are ways in
which you could, but still it happened naturally. It wasn't like you
created the sanctity, you just passively didn't avoid it. So תוספות says
there we would actually give you more latitude. That's all the more
problematic because that actually is קדושת קרבן kedushas korban so you can't
actually just transfer it to a penny. But anyway, תוספות deals with
that scenario.
The idea of the פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen is what again? Why
why would we not...?
There's a מצוה mitzvah to give five סלעים, selaim, you're not being
פודה podeh anything.
I understand, if you don't do it, the kid is קדוש. kadosh.
Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אשכחי רבי יונה לרבי אילא דקאי אפיתחא דצור. Ashchei Rabbi Yonah l'Rabbi
Ilai d'kai apitcha d'Tzur. So רבי יונה Rabbi Yonah found רבי אילא
Rabbi Ilai that was by the marketplace of צור, Tzur, or the
opening of the gate of the city of צור. Tzur. אמר ליה
קתני בהמה תעקר עבד מאי. Amar leh katani behemah t'akeir eved mai.
So according to רבי נתן Rabbi Natan that says he doesn't want
you buying in order to save the stuff for the Jewish ישוב
yeishuv in the land of ישראל. And he actually basically says if
you buy even things like animals and so on, you have to
destroy them. So then the same would be true about slaves. What
are you going to do if you buy a slave? How far
would he go? Would he say that you have to kill this
human being? עבד מאי? Eved mai? So עבד ישראל לא קמיבעיא לי.
Eved Yisrael lo k'mibaya li. If it's a Jewish I'm not asking.
כי קמיבעיא לי עבד עובד כוכבים. ki k'mibaya li eved oved kochavim.
Let's say it's a non-Jewish slave. How far would he go about
this קנס? knas? Maybe it wouldn't kill it, the בהמה behemah you
maim it, are you supposed to maim your non-Jewish slave if you
bought in this marketplace, if you don't hold of this reason about
מציל מידו? matzil miyado? So אמר ליה מאי קמיבעיא לך, Amar leh
mai k'mibaya lach, what's the problem? תניא עובדי כוכבים ורועי בהמה דקה
לא מעלין
ולא מורידין. Tanya ovdei kochavim v'ro'ei behemah dakah lo ma'alin v'lo moridin.
Idolaters and shepherds that you don't throw them down the well but
you don't save them from the well. So we don't try to
save their lives. So what does that mean? So it doesn't mean
that we actively mutilate them. So I mean if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, רש"י Rashi says, where's רש"י? Rashi? אותם
מן
הבור אם נפלו לתוכו אל יניחם וימותו Otam min habor im naflu
letocho al yanichem veyamutu and רש"י Rashi sounds like it means I
mean רש"י Rashi doesn't spell it out but he basically sounds like
basically what it would be that
yeah so yeah I was just seeing if there was any other
part of the רש"י Rashi I was missing. Anyway,
אלמא עובד כוכבים אסור להמיתו בידיים. Alma oved kochavim asur lehamito beyadayim.
Yeah, you're not allowed to directly kill him. Okay, so what are
you asking? Don't bother me, you're not allowed to kill him. Alright,
are you allowed to do something else indirectly like lock up the
door in front of them? Hopefully not. Hopefully he's saying come on,
it's a human life, give me a break. Okay, and hopefully it
also means you're not allowed to mutilate him either. Anyway, but all
of that was according to the approach that it was what do
you call it? That you don't do מציל מידם, Matzil Miyadam, but
now we're going to go back to the ברייתא Baraita of the
רבנן Rabbanan that you're allowed to do these things for מציל מידם.
Matzil Miyadam.
Where were we? אמר ליה רב ירמיה לרב זירא, Amar lei Rav
Yirmiya le-Rav Zeira, רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiya said to רב זירא, Rav
Zeira, קתני לוקחין מהם בהמה עבדים ושפחות, Katani lokechin mehem beheimah avadim
ushfachot, עבד ישראל או דלמא אפילו עבד עובד כוכבים. Eved Yisrael o
dilma afilu eved oved kochavim. The buying slaves, is it Jewish slaves
or even non-Jewish slaves? אמר ליה מסתברא עבד ישראל, Amar lei mistavra
eved Yisrael, presumably Jewish slaves. דאי עבד עובד כוכבים למאי איבעי ליה?
De'ei eved oved kochavim lemai ibai lei? What do you need a
non-Jewish slave for?
What do you mean, להביאם תחת כנפי השכינה, Lehaviam tachat kanfei hashechinah,
you're saving his soul?
I understand, which is what the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
It's a very strange, but exactly the answer was. Okay, so it
says רש"י Rashi says what מצוה mitzvah are you doing? But of
course why does it say what מצוה mitzvah you're doing when you
buy a בהמה? beheimah? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says כי אתא
רבין אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי אפילו עבד עובד כוכבים משום דמכניסן
תחת כנפי השכינה, Ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi afilu
eved oved kochavim mishum demachnisan tachat kanfei hashechinah, you're saving his soul,
okay? Of course, you know, do we have a מצוה mitzvah to
go ahead and to find non-Jews who and make them into non-Jewish
slaves, you know they were slaves of a non-Jew now we'll make
them a slave of a Jew so they're חייב במצוות? chayav bemitzvot?
Like you know it sounds a little like proselytizing whatever, it sounds
a little funny like we should be proactively invested in that process.
So that's one way of framing it. I actually prefer the other
way of framing it. אמר רב אשי אטו בהמה מאי תחת כנפי
השכינה איכא למימר? Amar Rav Ashi atu beheimah mai tachat kanfei hashechinah
ika lemeimar? Yeah and you're bringing your cow under כנפי השכינה? kanfei
hashechinah? אלא משום מיעוטייהו. Ela mishum mi'utaihu. The reason has nothing to
do with saving souls. The reason has to do with taking this
property away from non-Jews, I mean not legally taking it, and you
know and further entrenching the Jewish presence in the land of Israel.
So הכא נמי דממעטי שרי. Hacha nami demamati shari. Here too, same
reason. It's not has nothing you know and again, specific types of
property. It's real estate, cattle, slaves. Those are the things we want
to be in Jewish hands and not in non-Jewish hands. Okay,
now רש"י, Rashi, I'm reading it particularly about the land of Israel,
right? If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says משום מיעוטייהו
שממעיט עובדי כוכבים ומדלדלן. Mishum mi'utaihu shemama'it ovdei kochavim umedaldelan. Right, רש"י
Rashi doesn't sound like it's specifically land of Israel related, it's just
in general. But of course in general why I don't understand, I'm
taking a slave but they're getting my ten thousand dollars. Like why
does that mean that I'm making them less wealthy? So I really
think and by other things we're going to see in this chapter
in the גמרא it seems very much it's about these core things
that are about presence in the land and specifically about the land
of Israel. Let's just wrap this up. רב יעקב זבן סנדלא, Rav
Yaakov zavan sandala, רב יעקב Rav Yaakov bought a sandal in one
of these market days of the עבודה זרה. רב ירמיה זבן פיתא,
Rav Yirmiya zavan pita, he bought bread. אמר ליה חד לחבריה, Amar
lei chad le-chavreih, one said to the other, יתמא עבד רבך הכי?
Yatama avad rabach hachi? You orphan, you think your rabbi whatever would
act this way? You know, what doesn't don't you have a רבי?
Rebbe? Are you you know you go ahead you buy the stuff
at a שוק של עבודה זרה? shuk shel Avodah Zarah? אמר ליה
אידך יתמא עבד רבך הכי? Amar lei idach yatama avad rabach hachi?
You orphan, you think your רבי Rebbe would act this way? So
meaning they're both saying how could you have done such a thing?
But of course they both did it. Okay so ומר ומר מבעל
הבית זבני, Umar umar mibaal habayit zavni, so each one did it
because they bought from a homeowner and they didn't have to pay
a tax. וכל חד וחד סבר חבריה מתגר זבן Vechol chad vechad
savar chavreih mitagar zavan and each one was not דן חברו לכף
זכות. dan chaveiro lechaf zechut. It's a beautiful irony. Like I know
that I did it the right way but I see you, it's
like in some way I assume you did the wrong thing even
though I know myself that I did the right thing. Oh my
gosh. Anyway, דאמר רב אבא בריה דרב חייא בר אבא לא שנו
אלא בלוקח מן התגר דשקלי מכס מיניה אבל בלוקח מבעל הבית דלא
שקלי מכס מיניה מותר. De'amar Rav Abba breih de-Rav Chiya bar Abba
lo shanu ela belokech min hatagar deshakli meches mineih aval belokech mibaal
habayit delo shakli meches mineih mutar. Anyway, רב אבא בריה דרב חייא
בר אבא Rav Abba the son of Rav Chiya bar Abba says
it's only when you buy from a merchant that you pay the
tax, but if you buy from a homeowner where they don't take
the tax from him, it's permissible. אמר רב אבא בריה דרב חייא
בר אבא יומא הוה רבי יוחנן חד זימנא באתרא דקשקלי מכס אפילו
מבעל הבית הוה אסר. Amar Rav Abba breih de-Rav Chiya bar Abba
yoma hava Rabbi Yochanan chad zimna be'atra dekashakli meches afilu mibaal habayit
hava asar. רב יוחנן who makes this distinction, had he been in
the market on that day where he would see that they take
a tax even from the homeowners who sell, הוה אסר הוה אסר,
hava asar hava asar, he would have forbidden even from the home
buyers. And therefore you can't say that explanation because they're even taking
tax from the homeowners.
אלא היכי זבני? Ela heichi zavni? So how did they buy if
they're taking tax from the homeowner? מבעל הבית שאינו קבוע זבני. Mibaal
habayit she'eino kavua zavni. They bought from a homeowner that is not
even a regular you know there's the registered people who go to
the flea market, they're homeowners, they're not merchants, and then there's people
that are just passing through. Okay so fine, so there's a third
category. Sometimes they even take from the homeowners but they don't take
from the people that are passing through and selling things ad hoc.
מבעל הבית שאינו קבוע זבן. Miba'al Habayit she'eino kavua zaven. They bought
from a homeowner that is not even a regular, there's the registered
people who go to the flea markets, they're homeowners, they're not merchants,
and then there's people that are just passing through. Okay, so fine,
so there's a third category. Sometimes they even take from the homeowners,
but they don't take from the people that are passing through and
selling things ad hoc, and that was what happened to both of
them. But of course they both did it and then suspected their
colleague of doing it in the wrong way. All right, we will
end with this.